<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<Xml>
<head>
    <title>
        Language Specification Says...
    </title>
</head>
<body>
    <p>
        Before writing your code to handle V8 modules,
        it's useful to know what the language specification says.
        That not only makes it somewhat less unclear why the V8
        code is structured that way,
        but even makes the naming of V8 objects/functions/structure
        somewhat less opaque.
        For example, seeing the name <q>specifier</q> is less vague
        if you're aware that's the nomenclature used in the
        <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/#sec-hostresolveimportedmodule">ECMAScript
        specification</a>.
    </p>
    <h1>Lexical Environment</h1>
    <p>
        Recall that JavaScript has nested lexical scopes,
        which the language specification calls
        <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/#sec-lexical-environments">Lexical Environments</a>.
        Each lexical environment conceptually has a pointer to its outer/parent environment.
        So when the compiler tries to figure out what a symbol refers to,
        it looks for a definition in the current lexical environment,
        then its parent environment, then the parent of that environment, and so on.
    </p>
    <p>
        Eventually, of course, one finds an environment that has no parent environment,
        and that is deemed the
        <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/#global-environment">global environment</a>.
        This is pretty closely tied to the one-and-only
        <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/#sec-global-object">global object</a>
        of course, that is created before any JavaScript executes.
    </p>
    <p>
        The top-level scope in a "script" (JavaScript code that is not in a module) is essentially global.
        But the key difference with a module is that the module itself represents a lexical environment
        (whose parent is the global environment).
        That means nothing you declare in the module is going to clutter up the
        long-suffering global scope.
        If you want to allow an object/function in the module to be accessed outside the module,
        you must explicitly declare that with an export statement.
        If you want your code to "see" an object/function from another module,
        you must explicitly cause that to happen with an import statement.
    </p>
    <h1>Realms == Contexts, or Maybe Close Enough</h1>
    <p>
        The ECMAScript specification defines
        <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/#sec-code-realms">realms</a>,
        which basically are distinct instances of JavaScript that can only communicate via
        well-defined means.
        I would like to say that ECMAScript realms are identical to V8
        <a href="https://v8.dev/docs/embed#contexts">contexts</a>
        but that seems optimistic, so let's just say they're close to the same thing.
    </p>
    <p>
        You will care about this because the top-level code in each module must be
        executed no more than once for any given realm/context.
        To be explicit, consider a dummy module:
        <pre><code>
            // mymodule.js
            let PI = 3.14;
            export function TwoPI(){ return PI * 2; }
            export function CircleArea(radius) { return PI * radius * radius; }
        </code></pre>
        When this module gets executed
        (e.g., because some other code references <q>mymodule.js</q> with an import statement),
        it creates and intializes a variable and two functions.
        Those two functions are then available to be called from code outside
        this module.
        But (assuming the same context/realm) if the JavaScript compiler later
        runs into another import statement that refers to <q>mymodule.js</q>,
        your code is going to have to notice that you already loaded that module
        and it should not get executed again.
    </p>
    <h1>Module Import Recursion</h1>
    <p>
        If you make a graph with JavaScript modules as nodes and
        viewing their contained import statements as "arrows"
        pointing at other nodes,
        you can end up with cycles in your graph.
        A simple example is you import "a.js" which itself
        imports "b.js", which in turn happens to be
        importing some functions from "a.js".
        This is another reason you will be writing code that detects
        when a module has already been loaded.
    </p>
    <p>
        The first time JavaScript encounters an "import" statement,
        that could lead to a pretty long list of modules to import.
        In other words, the first module may import from other modules
        that in turn import from still other modules.
        This is most naturally defined as a recursive process that
        stops recursing when it hits modules that import no
        modules that have not already been loaded.
        However, just to be contrary, I will implement a non-recursive
        module load.
    </p>
    <h1>Specifiers and Ambiguity</h1>
    <p>
        As mentioned before, the ECMAScript specification is insulated
        from the outside world of files, URLs, etc. Those are your responsibility
        as the coder providing the host environment for V8.
        An import statement refers to a module via a string,
        which the
        <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/#sec-hostresolveimportedmodule">specification calls a "specifier"</a>.
        You will have to write code that, given one of those strings,
        brings the associated module text into memory and hands it to V8.
        That could be as simple as reading a file, or you might need to also
        be able to fetch URLs from across the web, or any other mechanism
        for storing the text of modules.
        For example, my particular application allows JavaScript no unfettered
        access to either a filesystem or the web,
        and I will be translating the "specifier" string into
        a database request, since all my module source code will be
        residing in an SQL database.
    </p>
    <p>
        Since modules are meant to be loaded only once,
        you are also in charge of handling the potential problem of different
        specifiers referring to the exact same module.
        For example, are "mymodule.mjs" and "MyModule.mjs" specifiers
        for the exact same module?
        Your intuitive answer may vary depending on whether you are accustomed
        to a Windows (case-insensitive filesystem) or *nix (case-sensitive filesystem) environment.
        Are "mymodule.mjs" and "./mymodule.mjs" specifiers that
        all refer to the same module?
        They will be if you are mapping specifiers directly onto a typical filesystem,
        which means your code has to notice that they both refer to the same module
        and not accidentally load another copy.
        Note that a module might contain some state crucial to its operation,
        and creating two copies may result in a mystifying bug at the JavaScript level.
    </p>
    <p>
        There are slightly different rules for modules and the more traditional
        JavaScript container which the
        <a href="https://www.ecma-international.org/ecma-262/#sec-ecmascript-language-scripts-and-modules">specification calls a "script."</a>
        Any code being run as the result of an "import" statement is presumably a module.
        But your code will need to decide whether (at least) that first chunk of code you
        are going to run is a "script" or a "module".
        Existing products adapting to the introduction of modules may have to
        use conventions, like "a .mjs extension means it's a module."
        I'm making a new project with no allegiance to any existing code,
        so I say the hell with that problem and I will assume everything
        I load for V8 to compile is going to be a module.
        Let's be modern and cool!
    </p>
    <h1>Module Unload</h1>
    <p>
        AFAIK, the language specification includes no notion of removing
        a module from memory after it has been imported. Unloading was
        a feature possible with Node's neo-module mechanism, "require."
        One might want such a thing for testing frameworks, and also
        during development when changed modules can be automatically detected
        and reloaded without having to shutdown and restart.
    </p>
    <p>
        Currently (spring 2020) this seems to be an
        <a href="https://github.com/nodejs/modules/issues/307">open issue</a>
        for Node.
        Is it important for your project?
        Something to think about.
        You might consider architectures in which it is possible
        to easily spin up a separate context, isolate, or Web Worker thread
        just for the purpose of loading a new or updated module.
        The idea being you could then easily terminate that context/isolate/thread
        in order to accomplish "unloading."
        That's a much larger granularity than just unloading a single
        module, of course, but also a much more tested scenario than
        any per-module unloading hack you might devise for the current V8.
    </p>
</body>
</Xml>

